import { useEffect, useReducer, useRef } from "react";
import Header from "./Header";
import Main from "./Main";
import Loader from "./Loader";
import Error from "./Error";
import TheStartScreen from "./TheStartScreen";
import Question from "./Question";
import Button from "./Button";
import PrevButton from "./PrevButton";
import Progress from "./Progress";
import FinishedScreen from "./FinishedScreen";
import Footer from "./Footer";
import Timer from "./Timer";

const initialData = [
  {
    question: "Which is the most popular JavaScript framework?",
    options: ["Angular", "React", "Svelte", "Vue"],
    correctOption: 1,
    points: 10,
  },
  {
    question: "Which company invented React?",
    options: ["Google", "Apple", "Netflix", "Facebook"],
    correctOption: 3,
    points: 10,
  },
  {
    question: "What's the fundamental building block of React apps?",
    options: ["Components", "Blocks", "Elements", "Effects"],
    correctOption: 0,
    points: 10,
  },
  {
    question:
      "What's the name of the syntax we use to describe the UI in React components?",
    options: ["FBJ", "Babel", "JSX", "ES2015"],
    correctOption: 2,
    points: 10,
  },
  {
    question: "How does data flow naturally in React apps?",
    options: [
      "From parents to children",
      "From children to parents",
      "Both ways",
      "The developers decides",
    ],
    correctOption: 0,
    points: 10,
  },
  {
    question: "How to pass data into a child component?",
    options: ["State", "Props", "PropTypes", "Parameters"],
    correctOption: 1,
    points: 10,
  },
  {
    question: "When to use derived state?",
    options: [
      "Whenever the state should not trigger a re-render",
      "Whenever the state can be synchronized with an effect",
      "Whenever the state should be accessible to all components",
      "Whenever the state can be computed from another state variable",
    ],
    correctOption: 3,
    points: 30,
  },
  {
    question: "What triggers a UI re-render in React?",
    options: [
      "Running an effect",
      "Passing props",
      "Updating state",
      "Adding event listeners to DOM elements",
    ],
    correctOption: 2,
    points: 20,
  },
  {
    question: 'When do we directly "touch" the DOM in React?',
    options: [
      "When we need to listen to an event",
      "When we need to change the UI",
      "When we need to add styles",
      "Almost never",
    ],
    correctOption: 3,
    points: 20,
  },
  {
    question: "In what situation do we use a callback to update state?",
    options: [
      "When updating the state will be slow",
      "When the updated state is very data-intensive",
      "When the state update should happen faster",
      "When the new state depends on the previous state",
    ],
    correctOption: 3,
    points: 30,
  },
  {
    question:
      "If we pass a function to useState, when will that function be called?",
    options: [
      "On each re-render",
      "Each time we update the state",
      "Only on the initial render",
      "The first time we update the state",
    ],
    correctOption: 2,
    points: 30,
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which hook to use for an API request on the component's initial render?",
    options: ["useState", "useEffect", "useRef", "useReducer"],
    correctOption: 1,
    points: 10,
  },
  {
    question: "Which variables should go into the useEffect dependency array?",
    options: [
      "Usually none",
      "All our state variables",
      "All state and props referenced in the effect",
      "All variables needed for clean up",
    ],
    correctOption: 2,
    points: 30,
  },
  {
    question: "An effect will always run on the initial render.",
    options: [
      "True",
      "It depends on the dependency array",
      "False",
      "In depends on the code in the effect",
    ],
    correctOption: 0,
    points: 30,
  },
  {
    question: "When will an effect run if it doesn't have a dependency array?",
    options: [
      "Only when the component mounts",
      "Only when the component unmounts",
      "The first time the component re-renders",
      "Each time the component is re-rendered",
    ],
    correctOption: 3,
    points: 20,
  },
];
export default function App() {
  const SECS_PER_QUESTION = 30;
  const initialState = {
    rawQuestions: [],
    questions: [],

    // 'loading', 'error', 'ready', 'active', 'finished'
    status: "loading",
    index: 0,
    answer: null,
    points: 0,
    highscore: 0,
    secondsRemaining: null,
    difficulty: "easy",
  };

  function reducer(state, action) {
    const data = state.rawQuestions.filter((data) => {
      return data.difficulty.toLowerCase() === action.payload;
    });
    switch (action.type) {
      case "dataReceived":
        return {
          ...state,
          rawQuestions: action.payload,
          status: "ready",
        };
      case "dataFailed":
        return { ...state, status: "error" };
      case "difficultySelected":
        return {
          ...state,
          difficulty: action.payload,
          questions: data,
        };
      case "start":
        return {
          ...state,
          status: "active",
          secondsRemaining: state.questions.length * SECS_PER_QUESTION,
        };
      case "newAnswer":
        const curQuestion = state.questions[state.index];

        return {
          ...state,
          answer: action.payload,
          points:
            action.payload === curQuestion.correctOption
              ? state.points + curQuestion.points
              : state.points,
        };
      case "nextQuestion":
        return {
          ...state,
          index: state.index + 1,
          answer: null,
        };
      case "prevQuestion":
        return {
          ...state,
          index: state.index - 1,
          answer: null,
        };
      case "finished":
        return {
          ...state,
          status: "finished",
          highscore:
            state.points > state.highscore ? state.points : state.highscore,
        };
      case "restart":
        return {
          ...initialState,
          rawQuestions: state.rawQuestions,
          questions: state.questions,
          status: "ready",
        };
      case "tick":
        return {
          ...state,
          secondsRemaining: state.secondsRemaining - 1,
          status: state.secondsRemaining === 0 ? "finished" : state.status,
        };
      default:
        throw new Error("Action Unknown");
    }
  }
  const [
    {
      questions,
      status,
      index,
      answer,
      points,
      highscore,
      secondsRemaining,
      difficulty,
    },
    dispatch,
  ] = useReducer(reducer, initialState);

  const totalQuestions = questions.length;
  const maxPossiblePoints = questions.reduce(
    (prev, cur) => prev + cur.points,
    0
  );

  useEffect(function () {
    dispatch({
      type: "dataReceived",
      payload: initialData,
    });
    dispatch({
      type: "difficultySelected",
      payload: "easy",
    });
  }, []);
  return (
    <div className="app">
      <Header />
      <Main>
        {status === "loading" && <Loader />}
        {status === "error" && <Error />}
        {status === "ready" && (
          <TheStartScreen
            questions={questions}
            totalQuestions={totalQuestions}
            dispatch={dispatch}
            difficulty={difficulty}
          />
        )}
        {status === "active" && (
          <>
            <Progress
              index={index}
              totalQuestions={totalQuestions}
              points={points}
              maxPossiblePoints={maxPossiblePoints}
              answer={answer}
            />
            <Question
              question={questions[index]}
              dispatch={dispatch}
              answer={answer}
            />

            <Footer>
              <Timer dispatch={dispatch} secondsRemaining={secondsRemaining} />
              <Button
                dispatch={dispatch}
                answer={answer}
                totalQuestions={totalQuestions}
                index={index}
              />
            </Footer>
          </>
        )}
        {status === "finished" && (
          <FinishedScreen
            points={points}
            maxPossiblePoints={maxPossiblePoints}
            highscore={highscore}
            dispatch={dispatch}
          />
        )}
        {status === "restart" && (
          <TheStartScreen
            totalQuestions={totalQuestions}
            dispatch={dispatch}
            difficulty={difficulty}
          />
        )}
      </Main>
    </div>
  );
}
